Welcome to the world of Google Colab.
구글 콜랍의 세계에 잘 오셨어요
You may already be very familiar with Google Colab, even if so, I hope I'll show you a couple of things
구글 콜랍에 대해 잘 아실지도 모르지만 그래도 몇 가지 보여드릴게요
But if not, uh, prepare for a great tool.
하지만 그게 아니라면 멋진 도구를 준비하세요
Um, and as I say, there's other competitors to Google Colab that are pretty similar.
콜랍과 비슷한 제품을 구글에 검색한 경쟁 업체도 있어요
Um, but this is where I suggest you start or do do the same sort of thing in your, uh, cloud compute
여기서 시작하거나 같은 걸 하길 권합니다 클라우드 컴퓨팅 플랫폼에서요
So the first thing you'll need to do is have a Google account if you don't already have one.
구글 계정이 없다면 가장 먼저 구글 계정을 만드세요
So when you go to this URL colab.research.google.com, uh, if you don't already have a Google account,
URL Colab으로 가보죠 연구요 구글 검색요 구글 계정이 없는 분들도
it will prompt you to, to, to to create one.
계정을 만들라고 할 거예요
And it's worth it.
그럴 가치가 있어요
There's going to be tons that we can do with it.
할 수 있는 일이 아주 많을 거예요
So uh, go ahead and do that if you need to.
그러니까 필요하면 그렇게 하세요
Um, but uh, for everybody else that has one, you will see this, um, which will give you some information
하지만 다른 분들을 위해 이걸 보시면 콜랍에 대한 정보가
about Colab.
나와요
There's a free tier and there is a paid tier.
무료 계층과 유료 계층이 있어요
There's an awful lot you can do just with the free tier.
무료 계층으로도 할 수 있는 게 정말 많아요
Um, and I think in theory, you should be able to do almost everything in our class with the free tier.
이론상으로는 무료로 수업 내용을 거의 다 들을 수 있어야 해요
It just might take longer.
시간이 좀 더 걸릴 뿐이죠
And the paid tier, you can control how much you spend, and it can be relatively small in a matter
유료 계층은 여러분이 얼마를 쓸지 결정할 수 있습니다 몇 달러 안에 비교적 적은 금액일
of a few dollars.
수도 있죠
So it's certainly something that I'd recommend you consider because it will allow you to get deeper
그래서 반드시 고려해 보시길 권합니다 더 깊이 훈련할 수 있고 아주
into training and it will be very satisfying.
만족스러울 테니까요 Get it
So, uh, when you come up with a new Colab notebook, it looks a bit like what gets served up right
콜랍 비트를 새로 만들면 바로 나오는 것과 비슷하죠
away.
주피터 공책과 아주 비슷해요
You have cells that can be code, or they can be text, and you can run code just by clicking in it
코드나 텍스트가 될 수 있는 셀이 있어요 클릭해서 실행하면 코드를 실행할
and running it.
수 있죠
And this is a kind of default one that comes up.
이건 기본값으로 나오는 거죠
What we can do is we can go file new notebook in drive.
드라이브에 새 공책을 철할 수 있어요
And it says in drive like that, because this notebook is created in your Google Drive, which is so
드라이브에서는 이렇게 된대요 구글 드라이브에서 만든 노트라서 아주 편리하죠
It has the same kind of construct as making Google Docs, making Google Sheets, and it's done in a
구글 문서나 구글 시트를 만드는 것과 같은 구성 구조를 갖고 있어요 다른 걸 공유하듯
way that you can share it just as you would share anything else.
공유할 수 있는 방식으로 이뤄졌죠
So here we are.
그래서 이렇게 됐죠
And the first thing that we see, what looks like a Jupiter notebook over here is a connect button.
제일 먼저 보이는 건 주피터 노트북처럼 보이는 연결 버튼이에요
And I'm going to show you we can start with change runtime type because it shows you the different kinds
런타임 형식 변경부터 보여드릴게요 다양한 런타임과
of runtime, the different kinds of VM that we can run a CPU.
CPU를 실행할 다양한 VM을 보여주니까요
In other words, a normal box that doesn't have one of these GPUs, graphics processing units that are
다시 말해 일반 상자에는 GPU가 없다는 거죠 그래픽 처리 장치가
so good at running, uh, parallel matrix maths that sits behind neural networks.
없는 상자요 신경망 뒤에 있는 평행 행렬 수학을 실행하는 장치요
So we can just choose a CPU box, which is very much available on the free tier.
CPU 상자를 선택하면 됩니다 무료 계층에서 많이 사용 가능하죠
There is a low end GPU box called a T4, which has a smaller GPU attached to it.
T4라는 저단 GPU 박스가 있는데 더 작은 GPU가 부착되어 있어요
This is available on the free plan with some rate limits in terms of how much you can use it, and it's
무료 요금제로도 구매하실 수 있어요 사용량에 따라 요금제한이 있지만 유료 요금제에서도
also very cheap on the paid plan.
아주 저렴해요
Um, there's an L4, which is a bit higher spec, and an A100, which is the strongest one and which
L4는 사양이 좀 더 높은 비트와 A100은 가장 강한 비트로
we will use when we want to do things quickly.
빨리 작업할 때 쓸 거예요
It does cost a little bit more, but still we're talking about dollars.
비트는 좀 더 들지만 그래도 달러잖아요
Not not not massive amounts.
엄청난 양은 아니죠
$10 will get you.
10달러면 Get이죠
I think it's it's, uh, with $10, you'd be able to to keep training for about 24 to 48 hours, uh,
10달러만 있으면 24시간에서 48시간 동안 계속 훈련할 수 있어요 그 상자를
using that box constantly.
계속 사용하면서요
So it's, uh, it's not not still not going to break the bank, but it is on the radar when you start
그래서 큰돈을 벌지는 못해도 a100을 많이 사용하면
using a100s a lot.
주목을 받게 되죠
Uh, so, um, and of course, you always get to see how much you're spending, and you can always choose
그래서 항상 얼마를 쓰는지 확인할 수 있고 언제든 더 싼 옵션이나
to to go with the cheaper option or go with a free option as you wish.
무료 옵션을 선택할 수 있어요.
And when you pick a box, you can have a high Ram version of it.
상자를 고르면 높은 램 버전이 나와요
And that's talking about the CPU, Ram, not the GPU.
GPU 말고 CPU, 램에 관한 거죠
The GPU Ram is associated with which instance you pick, but you can choose whether you want a high
GPU 램은 여러분이 고르는 인스턴스와 연결되어 있지만 높은 CPU, 램을 원하는지를
CPU, Ram, or not.
선택할 수 있어요
So let's just go with a CPU box with normal amount of Ram and connect to that box by pressing the connect
보통 양의 램을 가진 CPU 박스로 가서 연결 버튼을 눌러 박스에 연결할게요
It does take a little while to connect, because it has to hunt down a box and connect to it, but there
연결하는 데 시간이 좀 걸려요 상자를 찾아서 연결해야 하니까요 하지만 됐어요
we go.
지금 우린 상자에 연결돼 있어요
You go to this dropdown and say View Resources to see what you're working with.
이 드롭다운으로 가서 리소스 보기에서 작업 중인 걸 보세요
You can see the system Ram.
시스템 램이 보이죠
We've got like almost 13 gigs on this box, and we've got 225 gigs of disk space there.
이 박스는 거의 13기가이고 디스크 공간은 225기가예요
And I can go over here and I can type something like print hello Data Science World and run that.
여기로 가서 hello Data 과학 World 같은 걸 입력해 실행할 수 있어요
And shockingly, we get that message printed.
놀랍게도 그 메시지가 인쇄됐어요 get it
Uh, so, uh, hopefully no surprises there.
놀랄 일은 없길 바라요
It's a Jupyter notebook running in the cloud on a CPU.
주피터 노트북이 클라우드에서 CPU를 실행하고 있어요
A couple of other things to mention.
몇 가지 더 언급할 게 있어요
If you look down here, there's some useful stuff.
이 아래를 보면 유용한 게 있어요
This one here opens up your sort of browser, a file browser, onto your local disk.
이건 일종의 브라우저를 엽니다 파일 브라우저요 로컬 디스크로요
This local disk is ephemeral, and then it gets completely wiped once you finished using this box.
이 부분 디스크는 일시적이고 이 상자를 다 쓰면 완전히 지워져요
So consider it temporary and you can use it to be writing files there that you maybe are then going
임시라고 생각하고 파일을 작성할 수 있습니다 그 후 모델이나 데이터를
to upload your model or data to the Huggingface hub, um, which you will later download somewhere else.
H깅페이스 허브에 업로드 할 수 있죠 나중에 다른 곳에서 다운로드 할 수 있도록요
But this is temporary.
하지만 이건 일시적인 거예요
This is very important.
아주 중요한 거예요
This key is for what's called the secrets associated with your notebook.
이 열쇠는 당신 수첩과 관련된 비밀들을 여는 열쇠예요
And this is where you can put in the environment variables that you'll be able to access within your
여기 환경 변수를 입력할 수 있어요 노트북 안에서 액세스할 수 있는
notebook.
거죠
That should not be included in the code of the notebook.
그건 공책 코드에 포함되면 안 되죠
And what you'll see here is I have my anthropic API key.
여기 보이는 건 인류 API 키예요
I have my OpenAI API key and my hugging face token.
OpenAI API 키와 포옹하는 얼굴 토큰이 있어요
That's the thing we created in the last video, and I've got them associated with this notebook.
지난 비디오에서 만든 거죠 이 공책과 관련 있어요
You can just press Add New Secret to do that.
Add New 시크릿을 누르면 돼요
And it comes associated with all of my notebooks.
제 모든 공책과 관련이 있어요
Um, because I've got that set up as my colab secrets.
콜라베의 비밀이라고 적어 놨거든요
And you can create a new one by pressing Add New Secret there.
새 비밀 추가를 눌러 새 걸 만들 수 있어요
You can switch notebook access on here.
여기서 공책 사용 권한을 바꿀 수 있어요
I've just seen that there's a Create Gemini key option there.
제미니 만들기 핵심 옵션이 있네요
They're obviously a cross-selling to Gemini, and I know that I that I say that creating Gemini Keys
제미니 키스와 교차 판매를 하는 거죠 제미니 키스를 만드는 건 어려운
is is hard.
일이에요
Maybe they've got an easier path to creating Gemini API keys right there.
제미니 API 키를 만드는 더 쉬운 길이 있을지도 몰라요
So that would be worth trying.
시도해 볼 만하겠어요
If you haven't already gone through the rigmarole of setting up a Gemini API key.
제미니 API 키를 설정하는 복잡한 과정을 아직 안 거쳤다면요
Uh, so, um, and it's even I was going to say later we'll find out how to access your key from within
그래서... 나중에 말씀드리려고 했는데 주피터 수첩에서 열쇠에 접근하는 방법을 알아낼
the Jupyter notebook.
거예요
But wonderfully, they've given you the little, little scriptlet of code just there.
하지만 놀랍게도 작은 스크립트렛 코드를 제공했어요
That's what we'll be doing later to be accessing our secrets within the code on the right.
나중에 그렇게 할 겁니다 오른쪽 코드에 있는 우리 비밀에 접근하기 위해서요
So you should set these up when you get a chance.
그러니까 기회 있을 때 이런 거 좀 만들어 놔요 get it get it
When you're working with an actual notebook in particular, you flip this switch on to make sure that
특히 실제 노트북으로 작업할 땐 이 스위치를 켜서 셀에서
when you execute this code in a cell, it will have access to that secret.
이 코드를 실행할 때 해당 비밀에 접근하게 해야죠
And of course, as you can imagine, the sort of powerful thing about these secrets is that if you share
그리고 아시다시피 이 비밀의 강력한 힘은 이 공책을 다른 사람과 공유하면
this notebook with others, then they get all of your code.
코드를 모두 얻게 된다는 거죠. Get it.
But of course, they don't get your secrets shared.
물론 비밀을 공유하진 못하죠 Get it
They will have to enter in their own secrets in order to be able to run that code.
코드를 실행하려면 자신의 비밀을 입력해야 하죠
And similarly, of course, when I share notebooks for you to use, the same thing will apply.
마찬가지로 공책을 공유할 때도 같은 일이 적용되죠
You'll need to put in your own tokens in order to make take advantage of the code and run it against
코드를 활용하고 프론티어 모델에 적용하려면 여러분의 토큰을 넣어야
the frontier models or use your hugging face hub, um, or whatever.
합니다 또는 for 포옹 얼굴 허브 같은 걸 사용하세요
Okay, let's close that down.
이제 닫을게요
So let me just show you some of the more powerful boxes.
좀 더 강력한 상자들을 보여드릴게요
So you remember we can go here and go change runtime type.
기억하시겠지만 런타임 형식을 바꿀 수 있어요
Click on T4 to to use that box.
T4를 클릭하면 사용하실 수 있어요
And I did that earlier.
아까도 그랬고요
And I did that because uh, it can take a little while to connect to some of these boxes.
이렇게 한 이유는 상자에 연결하는 데 시간이 좀 걸리기 때문이에요
And with the really high spec boxes like A100, sometimes it just won't be available and you'll have
A100처럼 고성능 박스가 있으면 구하기가 힘들어서 2분 후에
to come back and try again two minutes later, and then it will be available.
다시 와서 시도해 봐야 구할 수 있어요
Invariably it becomes available after a couple of tries, but sometimes they are oversubscribed and
언제나 두어 번 시도하면 구할 수 있지만 너무 많이 팔려서 몇 번
it takes a few attempts.
시도해야 할 때도 있어요
So this is a T4 box.
이건 T4 박스인데요
If I do view resources, we'll see that we have again 12 and a bit of system Ram.
리소스를 보면 12개와 시스템 램이 약간 있네요
We have the same a slightly smaller hard drive, I think.
하드 드라이브는 좀 작지만요
I think it was two, two five before, but it's 200 whatever.
전에는 200달러였는데 지금은 200달러예요
That's plenty of disk space.
디스크 공간이 충분하죠
And we have a GPU with 15GB of Ram, and 15GB might sound like a huge amount of Ram to have for a GPU.
15GB 램이 있는 GPU가 있는데 GPU에 15GB 램은 너무 많은 것 같아요
But as you'll quickly discover when it comes to training deep neural networks, that is a kind of puny
하지만 심층 신경망 훈련에 관해선 자그마한 GPU 수준이지만
GPU, but it's good enough for our purposes.
우리 목적에는 충분하죠
We'll be able to use this for this class.
이 수업에서 활용할 수 있을 거예요
Um, uh, but but it just some things might take a long time.
하지만 어떤 일은 시간이 오래 걸릴 수도 있어요
Uh, this is a bit of code that I just copied from the original colab that Google prompted us with,
이건 코드인데 복사한 겁니다 구글 프롬프트 원본 콜라브에서요
which gives us a nice little, uh, printout of details behind this GPU, including how much memory
GPU 뒤의 세부 정보를 출력한 거죠 15GB에서 사용하는 메모리도
we're using out of the 15GB.
포함해서요
Although, of course, you can always watch it happening over here.
물론 여기서도 볼 수 있지만요
Uh, so this is the T4 box.
이게 T4 상자예요
I'm now going to show you the A100 box.
A100 박스를 보여 드릴게요
This is the super powered one, and I may splash out and use this from time to time.
이건 슈퍼 파워로 가끔 돈을 펑펑 쓰며 사용할 수도 있어요
Just in the spirit of keeping this class moving fast and showing you, uh, great results really quickly.
이 수업을 빠르게 진행하고 좋은 결과를 빨리 보여드리기 위한 정신이죠
Uh, if we view the resources, you'll see what's going on.
리소스를 보면 어떤 상황인지 알 수 있어요
Now, we've got a 40 gigabyte Ram, GPU and that that is a beefy GPU.
40기가 램이 있고 GPU는 아주 큰 GPU죠
That is something which will be able to use to do some hefty training.
격렬한 훈련을 하는 데 유용할 거예요
Um, and we can use this to print more details.
이걸 이용해서 더 자세한 걸 인쇄할 수 있어요
You can see that we are using two megabytes by, uh, when we're not doing anything out of the 40GB
2메가바이트로 사용하고 있는 걸 보실 수 있어요 사용 가능한 메모리 40GB에서 아무것도
of available memory.
하지 않을 때요
So that's the quick tour of what's going on with Colab.
콜랍에 대해 간단히 살펴봤는데요
The one other thing I'll mention is the share button up here.
또 한 가지 언급할 것은 공유 버튼이에요
Uh, if you press the share button, then you will see a very familiar interface, because if you use
공유 버튼을 누르면 아주 익숙한 인터페이스가 보일 겁니다 구글 드라이브를 사용한다면 구글
Google Drive at all, it looks just like everything else in Google Drive.
드라이브의 다른 모든 것과 똑같을 테니까요
You can share these notebooks and with different levels of permission with different groups, and use
허가 수준에 따라 다른 그룹과 이 노트를 공유할 수 있어요 협업하는
that as a way to collaborate really effectively.
데 효과적인 방법이죠
Uh, with friends, colleagues, coworkers on the, uh, the AI Jen AI projects that you're working
친구, 동료, 동료와 함께 인공지능 프로젝트를 진행하고 계시죠?
on.
물론 협업하기에 아주 효과적인 방법이죠
And that's one of the great benefits of using the Google Colab setup.
구글 Colab 설정이 가진 가장 큰 장점 중 하나죠
All right.
좋아요
I'll see you back for the next lecture.
다음 강의 때 뵙죠